<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>davecorning.com</title>
    <description>My personal space online.  A site about computers and technology.
</description>
    <link>http://davecorning.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://davecorning.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 14:10:31 +0900</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 14:10:31 +0900</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Lenovo Thinkpad T450s</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I love laptops, and I love finding laptops that can be made to run Linux
successfully (meaning sound, WiFi, video, function keys, hibernate/resume work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every 18-24 months, I get the urge to replace a perfectly functional, not-that-old
laptop with a newer model.  Given my specific requirements, I don’t usually have
too many models to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time around, I decided to go with the Lenovo Thinkpad t450s, because it
seemed like the best fit given all my requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;minimum&lt;/strong&gt; screen resolution of 1600x900.  136x768 is an immediate
disqualification.  The t450s I ordered came with a resolution of 1920x1080.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A replaceable hard drive.  I want the ability to swap out the stock drive
with my own SSD, which, in addition to driving down the cost of the laptop
itself, frees me from having to transfer hundreds of gigs of VM
guests, etc.  Since I’m using Linux, it’s also usually not necessary to
re-install the OS.  Just swap the drives and go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 13” or 14” &lt;strong&gt;non&lt;/strong&gt;-touchscreen display.  The t450s gave me the choice between
a touchscreen and non-touchscreen 14” display.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An Intel WiFi module.  I try to avoid those terrible Broadcom chipsets if I
can, primarily due to poor Linux drivers (and poor support).  A decent Intel WiFi
module is always about $20 away on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimum 12 GB of RAM.  This is a hard requirement.  I don’t want to have to
think about memory contention while running docker containers, postgres, redis,
apache, ruby/puma, VM guests, and the usual dozen-or-more-tab Firefox and Chrome
sessions (with JS debuggers).   I had initially looked at the Dell XPS developer
edition laptop, but it is limited to a maximum of 8 GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A battery that can last for at least 5 hours.  This is a recent one; it is
honestly the only gripe I have with my previous “daily driver” laptop.  I think
this is where the t450s really shines.  It comes with 2x 3 cell batteries (one
internal, one removable), and I was able to also buy an additional 6 cell battery.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A docking station (more of a “nice to have” than a hard requirement).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.lenovo.com/images/20034/Lenovo%20ThinkPad%20T450s%20Spec%20Sheet.pdf&quot;&gt;t450s&lt;/a&gt; has a core i7 Broadwell processor, 12 gigs of ram, a beautiful screen,
a very nice keyboard, a long battery life, and of course, it runs Linux,
although the Linux setup was not without its share of challenges.  (More on that in another post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-dave&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 23:27:56 +0900</pubDate>
        <link>http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello, World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, World!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to take another crack at hosting a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the intervening months since my previous attempt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octopress/octopress&quot;&gt;Octopress 3&lt;/a&gt; has been released (kind of), and trying out the new version was a perfect excuse to reboot the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-dave&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 19:03:07 +0900</pubDate>
        <link>http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/hello-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/hello-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
