<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>davecorning.com</title>
    <description>My personal space online.  A site about computers and technology.
</description>
    <link>http://davecorning.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://davecorning.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 13:48:04 +0900</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 13:48:04 +0900</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fedora 21 on the Lenovo Thinkpad T450s</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-of-may-2015-running-linux-on-a-laptop-with-an-intel-broadwell-cpu-is-not-without-its-share-of-minor-inconveniences-depending-on-your-use-case--fortunately-there-are-workarounds&quot;&gt;As of May, 2015, running Linux on a laptop with an Intel Broadwell CPU is not without its share of “minor inconveniences,” depending on your use case.  Fortunately, there are workarounds.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was able to rather effortlessly put Fedora 21 on
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/05/13/the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html&quot;&gt;my new thinkpad&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly encountered problems with video playback and VirtualBox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first assumption was that I might have a hardware problem, so I tried to rule out that possibility by booting into the Lenovo built-in hardware diagnostics software and running the complete suite of tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried a &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Kernel_Vanilla_Repositories&quot;&gt;vanilla mainline kernel&lt;/a&gt; and then I installed the most recent Fedora 22 beta, but the video and VirtualBox issues persisted.  The sneak peek of KDE in Fedora 22 does look pretty good, however. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem--1-video-playback-artifacts&quot;&gt;Problem # 1: Video playback artifacts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing any video through vlc reveals artifacts like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/simpsons_video_artifacts.png&quot; width=&quot;640px&quot; height=&quot;480px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came accross &lt;a href=&quot;http://askubuntu.com/questions/594451/14-04-thinkpad-t450-text-getting-messed-up-on-large-screens&quot;&gt;numerous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.launchpad.net/xserver-xorg-video-intel/+bug/1432194&quot;&gt;discussions&lt;/a&gt; regarding video problems on laptops that use Broadwell CPUs.  Although I’m not using Ubuntu, and I’m not experiencing the corrupted text problems discussed on those posts, the discussions nevertheless led me to a workaround.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would appear that my video corruption issues might be related to using &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SNA_%28computer_graphics%29&quot;&gt;SNA (Sandybridge’s New Acceleration)&lt;/a&gt;.  As I understand it, there are two acceleration methods for Intel GPUs; UXA (older, slower, more stable) and SNA.  Fedora 21 appears to prefer SNA, so I switched to UXA and restarted X and lo and behold, my video playback corruption issues are gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To switch from SNA to UXA, create the file &lt;code&gt;etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/20-intel.conf&lt;/code&gt;, paste the lines below and restart X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;# etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/20-intel.conf
Section &quot;Device&quot;
   Identifier  &quot;Intel Graphics&quot;
   Driver      &quot;intel&quot;
   Option      &quot;AccelMethod&quot;  &quot;uxa&quot;
EndSection
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly more work is needed on the SNA driver.  :-(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem--2-a-known-bug-with-virtualbox-on-broadwell-cpus-causes-x-to-lock-up&quot;&gt;Problem # 2. A known bug with VirtualBox on Broadwell CPUs causes X to lock up.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one mainfests itself when you try to launch a guest VM in VirtualBox (which is, as of May 2015, at version 4.3.26).  Launching any guest (I tried Windows 7 and Centos 6 guests with 4 GB and 1 GB of ram, respectively) triggered this lockup.  When it happens, the gui locks up hard.  Mouse and keyboard no longer respond, although the host is still pingable and can be accessed remotely via ssh; the only recourse at this point is to reboot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the opportunity to migrate the guests to KVM in the name of troubleshooting.  I was able to launch all guests successfully, which made me think this must be a VirtualBox bug on Linux hosts with Broadwell CPUs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further googling revealed at least &lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.fedoraforum.org/showthread.php?p=1731595&quot;&gt;one other user of fedora&lt;/a&gt; with the same problem.  The poster on the fedora forum helpfully shared some links to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.virtualbox.org/viewtopic.php?f=7&amp;amp;t=67516&amp;amp;p=319885&amp;amp;hilit=fedora#p319885&quot;&gt;VirtualBox forums&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.virtualbox.org/ticket/13961&quot;&gt;VirtualBox’s issue tracker&lt;/a&gt; which confirmed my earlier suspicions.  This is indeed a bug with VirtualBox on Broadwell CPUs, and it looks like it is being actively worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like I’ll be using KVM for a while until this bug is fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hardware-lister-lshw&quot;&gt;Hardware Lister (lshw)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One positive outcome of all this testing / bug hunting / googling / experimenting was the discovery of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ezix.org/project/wiki/HardwareLiSter&quot;&gt;lshw utility&lt;/a&gt;.  How cool!  I would encourage every owner of a laptop that runs linux to keep this utility within arm’s reach, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, as is always the case with Linux, the road is not without its share of bumps.  I’ll be keeping an eye on SNA in particular, and updating the blog as things change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-dave&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 13:46:27 +0900</pubDate>
        <link>http://davecorning.com/2015/05/20/fedora-21-on-the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://davecorning.com/2015/05/20/fedora-21-on-the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Lenovo Thinkpad T450s</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I love laptops, and I love finding laptops that can be made to run Linux
successfully (meaning sound, WiFi, video, function keys, hibernate/resume work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every 18-24 months, I get the urge to replace a perfectly functional, not-that-old
laptop with a newer model.  Given my specific requirements, I don’t usually have
too many models to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time around, I decided to go with the Lenovo Thinkpad t450s, because it
seemed like the best fit given all my requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;minimum&lt;/strong&gt; screen resolution of 1600x900.  136x768 is an immediate
disqualification.  The t450s I ordered came with a resolution of 1920x1080.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A replaceable hard drive.  I want the ability to swap out the stock drive
with my own SSD, which, in addition to driving down the cost of the laptop
itself, frees me from having to transfer hundreds of gigs of VM
guests, etc.  Since I’m using Linux, it’s also usually not necessary to
re-install the OS.  Just swap the drives and go.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 13” or 14” &lt;strong&gt;non&lt;/strong&gt;-touchscreen display.  The t450s gave me the choice between
a touchscreen and non-touchscreen 14” display.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An Intel WiFi module.  I try to avoid those terrible Broadcom chipsets if I
can, primarily due to poor Linux drivers (and poor support).  A decent Intel WiFi
module is always about $20 away on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimum 12 GB of RAM.  This is a hard requirement.  I don’t want to have to
think about memory contention while running docker containers, postgres, redis,
apache, ruby/puma, VM guests, and the usual dozen-or-more-tab Firefox and Chrome
sessions (with JS debuggers).   I had initially looked at the Dell XPS developer
edition laptop, but it is limited to a maximum of 8 GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A battery that can last for at least 5 hours.  This is a recent one; it is
honestly the only gripe I have with my previous “daily driver” laptop.  I think
this is where the t450s really shines.  It comes with 2x 3 cell batteries (one
internal, one removable), and I was able to also buy an additional 6 cell battery.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A docking station (more of a “nice to have” than a hard requirement).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.lenovo.com/images/20034/Lenovo%20ThinkPad%20T450s%20Spec%20Sheet.pdf&quot;&gt;t450s&lt;/a&gt; has a core i7 Broadwell processor, 12 gigs of ram, a beautiful screen,
a very nice keyboard, a long battery life, and of course, it runs Linux,
although the Linux setup was not without its share of challenges.  (More on that in another post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-dave&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 23:27:56 +0900</pubDate>
        <link>http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/the-lenovo-thinkpad-t450s.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello, World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, World!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to take another crack at hosting a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the intervening months since my previous attempt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/octopress/octopress&quot;&gt;Octopress 3&lt;/a&gt; has been released (kind of), and trying out the new version was a perfect excuse to reboot the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-dave&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 19:03:07 +0900</pubDate>
        <link>http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/hello-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://davecorning.com/2015/05/13/hello-world.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
